<doc name="Muen Separation Kernel">
 <author>Adrian-Ken Rueegsegger, Reto Buerki</author>
 <version>0.6</version>

 <latex_preamble>
  \usepackage{titlepic}
  \titlepic{\includegraphics[scale=0.4]{../../doc/images/muen.pdf}}

  \usepackage{tocloft}
  \setcounter{tocdepth}{1}

  \usepackage[head=30pt, lmargin=3.0cm, rmargin=3.0cm, bmargin=1.9cm, tmargin=3.2cm]{geometry}

  \usepackage{pgfgantt}

  \usepackage{hyperref}
  \hypersetup{
  pdftitle={Muen Kernel Specification},
  pdfsubject={Muen},
  pdfauthor={Adrian-Ken Rueegsegger, Reto Buerki},
  unicode=true,
  pdffitwindow=true,
  bookmarksnumbered=false,
  bookmarksopen=false,
  breaklinks=true,
  pdfborder={0 0 0},
  colorlinks=true,
  }

  \usepackage[T1]{fontenc}
  \usepackage{courier}
  \newcommand{\tablefont} {\fontfamily{pcr}\fontsize{7pt}{8pt}\selectfont}
  \let\oldlongtable\longtable
  \let\endoldlongtable\endlongtable
  \renewenvironment{longtable}{%
     \tablefont
     \oldlongtable
  }{\endoldlongtable}

  \begin{tikzfadingfrompicture}[name=flow fade]
   \shade[left color=transparent!0,
           right color=transparent!60] (0,0) rectangle (2,2);
  \end{tikzfadingfrompicture}

  \input{tikzstyle}

  \newenvironment{info}
  {\par
  \begin{list}{}{\leftmargin=1cm
  \labelwidth=\leftmargin}\item[\color{blue}\Large\ding{43}]}
  {\end{list}\par}
 </latex_preamble>

 <section id="introduction" label="Introduction" priority="0">
  <text priority="0">
   This document describes the Muen Separation Kernel (SK). It is intended to
   provide information and ultimately give a better understanding of the SK
   design and its implementation. Additionally a short overview of related
   topics such as system policy and integration is given. References for
   further reading are included as well. The Muen System Specification
   \cite{muen:system-spec} as well as the Muen Component Specification
   \cite{muen:component-spec} in particular should be viewed as the main
   complementary documents to this one. All three documents taken together make
   up the main documentation of the entire Muen project.

   The reader is expected to be familiar with concepts related to system-level
   software such as operating systems/microkernels, component-based systems as
   well as software development principles.

   Large parts of this document are generated based on annotations in the SK
   source code\footnote{Version: //{str:SK.Version.Version_String}}.
  </text>
  <section id="intro_structure" label="Document Structure" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    First, a high-level overview of the architecture, design and basic operation
    of the Muen Separation Kernel is provided in chapter \ref{overview}. The
    motivation for the architecture and the approach how kernel functionality is
    minimized and complexity is avoided are described. Next, the concepts of the
    system policy and configuration are quickly introduced. An overview of the
    operation of the kernel and its main functional building blocks are
    presented in sections \ref{overview_operation} through
    \ref{overview_crash_audit}. Chapter \ref{overview} closes with a discussion
    how subjects can interact and how covert channels can be avoided or limited
    in bandwidth on Muen systems.

    Chapter \ref{datamodel} describes how multicore support is realized by Muen
    and how kernel data is structured. This provides the reader with
    documentation on what different degrees of data sharing between CPU cores
    there are, what levels of coupling through data structures exist and how
    the data is initialized.

    The following chapters \ref{interface_section} and
    \ref{cpu_global_variables_section} document all kernel data structures
    grouped by the categories introduced in the previous chapter. The purpose of
    each data structure is given as well as its type and layout.

    Next, the kernel's direct use of devices is described. Aside from the
    interrupt controller and IOMMU, Muen's use of the VMX-preemption timer is
    presented as well as how diagnostics information is provided by the debug
    build of the kernel.

    Chapter \ref{implementation} describes the kernel implementation in detail.
    Aside from kernel initialization and exit handling the crash audit, subject
    state and VMCS management are documented. Then an enumeration of all Ada
    packages that make up the kernel code base is given.

    A quick introduction of SPARK and the verification process as well as tools
    is given in chapter \ref{verification_and_validation}. Furthermore, a
    summary of verification conditions of the SPARK proofs for the Muen SK
    \footnote{based on the same version this document was generated from} is
    presented.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="intro_source_code" label="Source Code" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    This section gives a short overview of the Muen source code. It describes
    where and how to download it and presents a brief description of the source
    tree layout.
   </text>
   <section id="intro_source_code_get" label="Obtaining the Source Code" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     The source code of the Muen project is hosted in the official Git
     repository which is located at \url{https://git.codelabs.ch/muen.git}. \\

     To obtain the source, clone the Git repository as follows: \\

     \verb!git clone --recursive https://git.codelabs.ch/muen.git!
    </text>
   </section>
   <section id="intro_source_code_layout" label="Source-Tree Layout" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     The top-level directory of the Muen source tree contains a README file which
     gives a good overview of the key aspects of the Muen project. Furthermore
     it gives practical advice on how to get started including references to
     further resources.

     In the following, a brief description of each sub-directory and what it
     contains is given:

     \begin{description}
        \item[common/] \hfill \\
        Source code packages shared between the kernel and components.
        \item[components/] \hfill \\
        Implementations of various components and libraries, such as device
        drivers (e.g. AHCI, PS/2) or Subject Monitor for Muen Linux. These are
        utilized to realize different Muen Systems and can be reused in any
        component-based system running on top of Muen.
        \item[config/] \hfill \\
        Compiler and Proof tool configuration used when building the Muen tools,
        Components as well as the kernel.
        \item[contrib/] \hfill \\
        Third-party software required for building some tools and components.
        \item[deploy/] \hfill \\
        This directory contains build system facilities to enable the simple
        deployment of Muen system images to supported hardware platforms. Refer
        to the README for further details.
        \item[doc/] \hfill \\
        Contains documents describing different elements of the Muen project.
        The Master Thesis \emph{An x86/64 Separation Kernel for High Assurance}
        originally written in 2013 is also located in this directory.
        \item[emulate/] \hfill \\
        This directory contains build system facilities to enable the emulation
        of Muen systems under nested QEMU/KVM. Refer to the README for
        further details.
        \item[kernel/] \hfill \\
        This directory contains the implementation of the Muen Separation Kernel.
        \item[pack/] \hfill \\
        This directory contains build system facilities for the assembly of
        bootable Muen system images.
        \item[policy/] \hfill \\
        Provides various Muen system policies such as the demo system, as well
        as specifications for a selection of hardware platforms.
        \item[projects/] \hfill \\
        Support utilities used by the Muen build process are located in this
        sub-directory.
        \item[rts/] \hfill \\
        Zero-Footprint Ada runtime used by the Muen SK as well as native
        Ada/SPARK component implementations.
        \item[tools/] \hfill \\
        Contains the Muen toolchain used for building and assembling a Muen
        system image. For further details, refer to \cite{muen:system-spec}.
     \end{description}
    </text>
   </section>
  </section>
 </section>

 <section id="overview" label="Overview" priority="0">
  <text priority="0">
   This section gives an overview of the design and architecture of the Muen
   Separation Kernel.
  </text>
  <section id="overview_architecture" label="System Architecture" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Muen is an open-source Separation Kernel implemented in the SPARK
    programming language, which has been shown to be free from certain bug
    classes through the application of formal methods. It leverages the
    virtualization extensions provided by the hardware platform to securely
    isolate subjects and devices.

    \begin{figure}[ht]
     \centering
     \input{graph_arch}
     \label{fig-muenarch}
     \caption[Execution of VMs and native subjects]{Execution of VMs and native
      subjects on top of the Muen SK. The kernel is the only software running in
      the privileged Intel VT-x root mode while all Subjects execute in
      unprivileged non-root mode.}
    \end{figure}

    The Muen SK is the only part of the system running in VMX
    root mode: all subjects, be it fully-fledged VMs or small, native subjects,
    execute with lower privileges in non-root mode. By design, no code is
    executed in user-space (ring 3) of VMX root mode. This enables Muen to
    completely avoid code for handling Syscalls/Ring-3-to-Ring-0 transitions,
    significantly reducing the code size and complexity.

    Deterministic runtime behavior of the SK is achieved by avoiding
    long-running code paths and preemption of kernel code. During kernel
    execution, external interrupts are disabled and the proof of absence of
    runtime errors assures that no exceptions occur. Furthermore, the absence of
    any kind of dynamic resource management and the fixed, cyclic scheduler
    contribute to the highly deterministic runtime behavior of the kernel.

    The sole purpose of the kernel is to provide temporal and spatial
    isolation for subjects running on top of it. By design, all non-essential
    functionality has been removed from the kernel. This results in a
    significant reduction of code size and complexity. Figure \ref{fig:sksubs}
    illustrates parts that usually make up an Operating System and the subset
    that is implemented by the Muen SK.

    \begin{figure}[ht]
     \centering
     \input{graph_sk0}
     \caption[Complexity reduction of Muen SK]{Complexity reduction of Muen SK
     compared to a classical, monolithical Kernel.}
     \label{fig:sksubs}
    \end{figure}

    Since resource allocation is static, there is no need for resource
    management at runtime. Additionally, Muen does not provide a complex
    hypercall API. Subjects can only trigger events, such as sending a signal to
    a specific subject, that have been defined in their entirety in the policy
    at integration time.  Virtualization events such as traps are not handled by
    the SK but instead reflected to components as specified in the policy.

    Static configuration also frees the kernel from any policy decisions: the
    runtime behavior is precisely specified in the system policy which, in turn,
    enables detailed analysis of the system prior to its execution.

    Further functionality must be implemented in unprivileged subjects. Complex,
    abstracted IPC mechanisms, which are usually provided by classical
    microkernels, are not part of the Muen kernel.

    In addition to the minimization of kernel functionality, care is also taken to
    ensure that the implementation is made as comprehensible and understandable
    as possible. In particular, the use of complicated algorithms or complex
    language constructs is deliberately avoided.
   </text>
  </section>
   <section id="overview_policy" label="Policy" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     This section gives a short description of the Muen system policy and how
     it relates to the kernel. A detailed description of the Muen System
     Specification can be found in the corresponding document
     \cite{muen:system-spec}.

     In the context of Muen, integration of a system is defined as the process
     of assembling a runnable system image out of constituent parts, such as
     compiled kernel and subject code, generated data structures (e.g.
     page tables), etc following a system description.

     The configuration of a Muen system takes place during the integration by
     means of a \emph{policy} in XML format. The policy includes a declaration
     of all existing hardware resources of the target platform, the subjects to
     be executed with their assigned resources as well as the scheduling plan.
     The plan specifies exactly when a subject should run on which CPU and for
     how long.

     Information flows between subjects are defined in their entirety in the
     policy. So-called memory channels declare directional writer/reader
     relationships and assignment of physical memory or devices for shared
     usage is also possible. Unassigned resources are not available during
     runtime.

     From the information specified in the policy, the Muen toolchain
     generates the actual configuration of the
     hardware, which is merely applied by the kernel at runtime. For example,
     the page tables for a subject are generated, which the kernel applies
     accordingly, when the associated subject is executed. The SK has no
     knowledge of the exact layout of the page tables and which memory areas are
     accessible to a subject. In fact, these data structures are not even mapped
     into the address space of the kernel since they remain static and do not
     need to be accessed.

     As part of the integration, numerous validations are carried out. Each
     check ensures a specific functional or security-relevant system property,
     such as for example accessibility of sensitive system memory to subjects.
     These properties can, where desirable, be manually audited or visualized.
    </text>
   </section>
   <section id="overview_config" label="Configuration" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     Relevant aspects of the system are transformed by the \texttt{mugenspec}
     tool to data structures in the form of SPARK source files, which are
     represented by the Ada package hierarchy \texttt{Skp}. These include for
     example IRQ routing information, scheduling plans, initial subject state
     etc, see section \ref{Skp} for detailed documentation.

     Whenever the kernel needs to perform a policy decision, it simply consults
     the corresponding table, which contains the necessary information. For
     example when a hardware interrupt is raised, the kernel performs a lookup
     in the \texttt{Skp.Interrupts.Vector\_Routing} array using the IRQ number
     as index. The entry specifies which subject the recipient of the interrupt
     is, as well as the vector number to inject. With this information, the
     kernel can mark the corresponding interrupt as pending and resume regular
     operation.

     More information regarding the policy processing by the Muen toolchain can
     be found in the Muen System Specification document \cite{muen:system-spec}.
    </text>
   </section>
   <section id="overview_operation" label="Kernel Operation" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     The Muen kernel has two main entry points: system initialization and the
     scheduler loop. Upon start of a system the kernel puts the CPU in the
     appropriate state by setting up the MMU and transitioning into VMX
     root-mode. After setting up the interrupt controllers, IOMMU and when all active
     CPU cores are ready, the execution of the initial subject is started by
     means of a VM-Entry. Detailed description of kernel initialization is
     given in section \ref{impl_kernel_init}.

     On VM-Exit the hardware invokes the scheduler subprogram since it has been
     set as the kernel entry point in the subject VMCS data structure. The
     kernel synchronizes data from the VMCS to the subject state data structure
     in memory. After handling the exit condition, the next subject is prepared
     by synchronizing the VMCS with values from the subject state and execution
     is started by performing a VM-entry. The kernel control-flow is illustrated
     by figure \ref{fig:kernel-operation}. A detailed description of the
     implementation is given in section \ref{impl_exit_handler}.

     \begin{figure}[h]
      \centering
      \input{graph_operation}
      \caption{Kernel control-flow}
      \label{fig:kernel-operation}
     \end{figure}
    </text>
   </section>
   <section id="overview_separation" label="Separation of Subjects" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     The kernel implements the communication policy by separating subjects
     spatially and temporally. It does not have to perform any policy decisions
     because it is static and does not change. Thus, the Muen SK can be seen as
     a policy enforcement engine.

     Spatial separation of main memory is enforced through the use of hardware
     memory protection (MMU and IOMMU). The corresponding page tables are made
     active whenever a subject is executed. As a consequence, subjects have only
     access to the memory resources assigned to them.
     DMA-capable devices are restricted to the memory allowed by the system
     policy. This is enforced by the IOMMU via DMA Remapping (DMAR).

     Architectural state, such as processor and FPU registers, is saved to an
     associated memory region when subjects change. The state of the subject to
     be executed is completely restored. An in-depth description of the
     implementation is given in section \ref{impl_subjects_state}.

     Access rights to model-specific registers (MSRs) as well as I/O ports of
     devices are determined via MSR and I/O bitmaps, see Intel SDM Vol. 3C,
     "24.6 VM-Execution Control Fields" \cite{intelsdm}.
     Unauthorized access is intercepted by the processor and the execution of
     the subject is interrupted. The incident is handled according to the exit
     handling of the subject specified in the policy by looking up the
     appropriate action in the subject's VM-Exit event table.

     Device interrupts are also protected by hardware: by using interrupt
     remapping, devices can only generate the interrupt vectors assigned in the
     policy.

     Temporal isolation of subjects is implemented by the scheduler, described
     in the following section \ref{overview_scheduling}.
    </text>
   </section>
   <section id="overview_scheduling" label="Scheduling" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     This section presents the design and operation of the Muen kernel scheduler
     and the chosen scheduling algorithm.

     Scheduling is defined as the process of selecting a subject and giving it
     access to its assigned system resources for a certain amount of time. The
     main resource is processor time, which enables a subject to execute
     instructions in order to perform its task.

     A key objective of the scheduler is to provide temporal isolation by
     preventing any interference between subjects. To achieve this, scheduling
     is done in a fixed, cyclic and preemptive manner according to a plan
     specified in the system policy.

     Subjects are executed for a fixed amount of time, before being forcefully
     preempted by the scheduler. Preemption means that regardless of what
     operations a subject is currently performing, its execution is suspended
     when the allotted time quantum has been consumed. Suspension means the
     current state like CPU register contents is saved to the data structure
     associated with the subject. After a subject has been suspended, the
     scheduler restores the state and executes the next subject for a given
     amount of time.

     Scheduling information is declared in a \emph{scheduling plan}. Such a plan
     is part of the policy and specifies in what order subjects are executed on
     which CPU core and for how long (see \ref{Skp.Scheduling}). The task of
     the scheduler is to enforce a given scheduling regime.

     A scheduling plan is specified in terms of frames. A \emph{major frame}
     consists of a sequence of minor frames. When the end of a major frame is
     reached, the scheduler starts over from the beginning and uses the first
     minor frame in a cyclic fashion. This means that major frames are
     repetitive. A \emph{minor frame} specifies a subject and a precise amount
     of time. This information is directly applied and enforced by the scheduler.

     Figure \ref{fig:example-major-frame} illustrates the structure of a major
     frame.  The major frame consists of four minor frames. Minor frame 2 has
     twice the amount of ticks than the other minor frames, which have identical
     length. Time progresses on the horizontal axis from left to right.

     When the major frame starts, subject 1 is scheduled for the length of minor
     frame 1, followed by a switch to subject 2. After that the two subjects are
     again scheduled in alternating fashion.

     \begin{figure}[ht]
      \centering
      \input{graph_major_frame}
      \caption{Example major frame}
      \label{fig:example-major-frame}
     \end{figure}

     On systems with multiple CPU cores, a scheduling plan must specify a
     sequence of minor frames for each processor core. For any given major
     frame, the sum of all minor frame time slices of a given CPU core must
     amount to the same time duration, i.e. a major frame has the same length
     on all cores. In order for the cores to not run out of sync, all CPUs
     synchronize by means of a barrier prior to starting a new major frame.
     Additionally, CPUs that switch minor frames at the same time also
     synchronize the execution of the next minor frame.

     An example of a scheduling plan for multiple CPUs is depicted in
     figure \ref{fig:example-scheduling-plan}. It illustrates a system with two
     CPUs that execute various subjects indicated by different colors.

     \begin{figure}[ht]
      \centering
      \input{graph_scheduling_plan}
      \caption{Example scheduling plan}
      \label{fig:example-scheduling-plan}
     \end{figure}

     CPU0 is executing the same subject for the whole duration of the major
     frame. The second CPU is executing two subjects (blue
     and green) in alternating order. As can be seen, subject green is granted
     more CPU cycles than subject blue. All CPUs of the system wait on a barrier
     at the beginning of a new major frame.  This guarantees that all logical
     CPUs of a system are in-sync when major frames change.

     The scheduler is also kept simple by the fact that subjects never migrate
     between cores: they can only be scheduled on one particular CPU. This
     invariant is checked and enforced during the policy validation step
     (see \cite{muen:system-spec}).

     Since a system performs diverse tasks with different resource requirements,
     there is a need for some flexibility with regards to scheduling. To provide
     this degree of freedom while keeping the kernel complexity low, multiple
     scheduling plans can be specified in the system policy. By defining a
     distinct plan for each anticipated workload in the policy, the scheduling
     regimes are fixed at integration time.

     The privileged subject $\tau$0 is allowed to elect and activate one of the
     scheduling plans. It specifies the active scheduling plan using a global
     variable called \texttt{New\_Major} which currently makes up the entirety of
     the $\tau$0-Kernel interface, see \ref{SK.Tau0_Interface.New_Major}. On
     major frame change, the BSP copies this value to the global
     \emph{current major frame ID}. The value is exclusively written by the BSP
     while it is used by all cores to determine the currently active major
     frame, see \ref{SK.Scheduler.Global_Current_Major_Frame_ID}.

     Refer to \cite{muen:system-spec} for a description of $\tau$0 as well as
     the motivation behind it.
    </text>
   </section>
   <section id="overview_interrupts" label="Interrupts" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     Devices can generate hardware interrupts that must be delivered to the
     subject that controls the device. The system policy defines which hardware
     interrupt is assigned to what subject and what vector should be injected if
     such an interrupt occurs.

     Since resource allocation is static, a global mapping of hardware interrupt
     to destination subject including the interrupt vector to deliver, is
     generated at integration time, see the \texttt{Skp.Interrupts} package in
     section \ref{Skp.Interrupts}. The kernel uses the \texttt{Vector\_Routing}
     array at runtime to determine the destination subject that constitutes the
     final recipient of the interrupt.

     The IRQ trigger mode is also designated by the \texttt{Skp.Interrupts}
     package. Masking of the IRQ is done by the kernel for level-triggered IRQs.
     A subject can unmask the IRQ by triggering an event that has the
     corresponding unmask IRQ action specified in the policy.

     Each subject has a bitmap of 256 pending interrupts, each entry
     corresponding to the vector number of the interrupt. An interrupt is
     forwarded to a subject by setting the correct bit in the data structure
     associated with the destination subject. Once execution of a subject is
     resumed, the kernel checks the pending interrupts and, if one is pending,
     injects it, which completes the delivery of the interrupt. If multiple
     interrupts are pending, the one with the highest vector number is
     processed.

     Subjects can control interrupt injection by setting or clearing the
     \emph{Interrupt enable flag} \footnote{RFLAGS.IF}. As long as the flag is
     clear, the kernel will not inject any pending interrupts. A subject can use
     the \texttt{cli} and \texttt{sti} instructions to clear/set the flag.

     To simplify the kernel control flow, the VMX External-interrupt exiting
     feature is used, see Intel SDM Vol. 3C, "24.6.1 Pin-Based VM-Execution
     Controls". With this control set, an external interrupt results in a VM
     exit. This means that instead of a separate interrupt handler routine, the
     same kernel entry point as any other VM exit is invoked by the hardware.
     The appropriate VM exit reason set by the hardware designates that the
     cause was an external interrupt and the interrupt handler routine is
     executed.  The "Acknowledge Interrupt on Exit" VM-Exit control is
     leveraged, so the hardware acknowledges the interrupt controller and stores
     the interrupt vector in the VM-exit interruption-information field, see
     Intel SDM Vol. 3C, "24.7.1 VM-Exit Controls".

     Thus, interrupt handling is implemented as specified in Intel SDM Vol. 3C,
     "33.3.3.3 Processing of External Interrupts by VMM".

     Spurious or invalid interrupts that have no valid interrupt to subject
     mapping are ignored by the kernel.
    </text>
   </section>
   <section id="overview_exceptions" label="Exceptions" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     We distinguish hardware exceptions that occur in VMX non-root mode, while
     executing a subject, and in VMX root mode when the kernel is operating.

     As the kernel is implemented in the SPARK programming language
     (see section \ref{verification_spark}) with a prove of absence of runtime
     errors, exceptions during regular operation in VMX root-mode are not
     expected. If for some unexpected reason (e.g.  non-maskable interrupt NMI)
     an exception occurs, it indicates a serious error. In that case, a crash
     audit record is filled with the appropriate error information and the
     system is halted. Refer to section \ref{impl_crash_audit} for a detailed
     description of the Crash Audit implementation.

     In the case of an exception being caused by the execution of a subject, the
     kind of exception handling depends on the vCPU profile of the running
     subject. The vCPU configuration of each subject is specified as part of the
     system policy. If the subject is \emph{not} allowed to handle a particular
     exception itself, then a VM exit occurs with the exit reason indicating the
     cause. The kernel handles the trap like any other exit and consults the
     subject's trap table to determine the appropriate action as specified in
     the policy, e.g. switching to a monitor subject.

     Subjects may be allowed to process exceptions themselves, e.g. a VM subject
     performing its own page fault handling. In this case, an exception is
     directly delivered to the subject's exception handler via the subject's
     IDT. The kernel is not involved at all in this case.
    </text>
   </section>
   <section id="overview_crash_audit" label="Crash Audit" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     Every software system should provide a mechanism for auditing important
     events. However, overly intricate audit implementations can quickly lead to
     complexity throughout the code base. In case of the Muen kernel, only two
     important events that require auditing have been identified: one is
     \emph{kernel started} and the other is a \emph{fatal error condition}
     resulting in an emergency halt.

     Note that on the system level, there are certainly many more audit-worthy
     events. However these can be handled by appropriate error handling routines
     inside subjects, or by dedicated audit subjects using existing mechanisms
     (e.g. events). The kernel does not need to provide any additional,
     audit-specific functionality.

     The first event is inherent in the execution of the kernel after a
     successful system start. If there is an error during early machine
     initialization before the actual Muen-based system starts execution, then
     there is no way for the kernel to recognize and report such an event.
     However, once the kernel does start execution, the successful system start
     has occurred so in that sense the event becomes self-evident through
     running code.

     The crash audit mechanism is in charge of covering the second case and thus
     handling fatal, unrecoverable errors which lead to immediate system halt
     and subsequent system reset. Its main purpose is to record information
     regarding the error condition and the current system state to enable
     administrators to identify and determine the cause of the issue.

     Audit information is stored in a dedicated, uncached memory region which
     retains its contents across system reboots. This region is mapped by all
     kernel instances on each CPU. Read access may be granted to a subject to
     enable audit readout for further processing, e.g. debug server outputting
     the information via serial log. Note that processing of the audit
     information may also be done outside of a Muen system, e.g. by a crash
     audit aware boot loader.

     When a fatal crash occurs, the kernel allocates a free audit entry, sets
     the appropriate reason for the current cause and fills the remaining
     context fields with relevant data. Multiple cores may experience a fatal
     failure condition at the same time (e.g. faulty hardware resulting in
     Machine-Check Exceptions broadcastet to all CPU cores). Since each kernel
     instance performs audit entry reservation atomically, this scenario is
     supported.

     After a reboot, the crash audit entries may be inspected. Entries are
     identified as current, when the boot count of the header and the generation
     in the given entry match. Otherwise, the audit entry contains stale
     information from a previous crash which has already been processed. This
     enables reliable identification of current audit entries to avoid duplicate
     processing.
    </text>
   </section>
   <section id="overview_interaction" label="Subject Interaction" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     Compared to applications or virtual machines running on classical kernels
     (e.g. monolithic or microkernel), subjects have very limited means to
     influence the overall system. Only the resources assigned in the policy are
     accessible and the interaction with the SK is limited to the following
     mechanisms.

     Subjects can trigger events \emph{statically} defined in the policy. If
     there is a valid event number, the kernel executes the action defined by
     the event. Invalid event numbers are ignored. Events can be thought of as a
     very static form of \emph{hypercalls}, that can be actively invoked by a
     subject.

     When so-called \emph{traps} occur, e.g. access to an unauthorized memory
     region, a trap table also specified in the policy is consulted. Similar to
     handling of events, the defined action is executed. In contrast to events,
     traps generally happen whenever a subject performs an action that is
     disallowed by the policy, e.g. attempt to read the Timestamp Counter (TSC).
     A trap always interrupts subject execution and invokes the kernel.

     Several types of traps are directly handled by the kernel as they are used
     to implement kernel functionality. These traps are:

     \begin{description}
      \item[External Interrupt] \hfill \\
       Processing of external device interrupts
      \item[VMX-preemption timer expired] \hfill \\
       Main kernel timer used for scheduler implementation.
      \item[Interrupt window] \hfill \\
       Mechanism for delivery of pending subject interrupts.
      \item[Exception or non-maskable interrupt (NMI)] \hfill \\
       Handling of Machine-Check Exceptions (MCEs) and NMIs.
      \item[VM-entry failure due to machine-check event] \hfill \\
       Further handling of MCEs.
      \item[Xsetbv instruction] \hfill \\
       Handling of XCR0 register which controls the extended processor/FPU
       features and state.
     \end{description}

     A detailed description of the implementation is given in section
     \ref{impl_exit_handler}. For a list of all VM exit reasons, refer to Intel
     SDM Vol. 3D, "Appendix C VMX Basic Exit Reasons" \cite{intelsdm}.

     The last interaction option is the \emph{timed event} mechanism. Each
     subject can define an event number and a time at which the event should be
     triggered. At the beginning of each time slice, the kernel checks whether
     the event trigger value belonging to the subject to be executed has
     expired. If this is the case, the event designated by the event number is
     treated in the same way as the regular event mechanism.

     An important use case for traps and events that enable to change the
     currently active subject, is running a subject that depends on a monitor
     subject for emulation of certain operations, e.g. serial device emulation.
     In this scenario, whenever a subject performs an operation that triggers a
     trap the policy specifies an event of mode \emph{switch} with the target
     being the monitor subject. This instructs the kernel to hand over execution
     to the monitor, in effect reflecting the trap. The monitor subject can then
     determine the cause for the trap based on the information available in the
     subject state that is mapped into the monitor's address space. It can then
     emulate the appropriate action by changing the subject's state and finally
     hand over execution back by triggering an event that has been specified in
     the policy to resume the origin subject. Prior to resumption the kernel
     will synchronize the subject state to the VMCS, effectively continuing
     execution of the origin subject with the new, adjusted state.

     Through the use of the event mechanism, the vast majority of traps is
     handed over to a second subject to process. Only a few event actions are
     handled directly by the kernel: unmask IRQ, system panic, reboot and
     poweroff, see also \ref{impl_handle_source_event}.
    </text>
   </section>
   <section id="overview_covert_channels" label="Avoidance of Covert Channels" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     So called \emph{side channels} allow attackers to deduce information about
     internal, secret state of an unsuspecting subject by observing e.g. the
     memory consumption or changes in the micro-architectural state of the
     hardware. The victim process is unintentionally leaking sensitive
     information through the side channel, which is used by the attacker to
     infer data it is not supposed to have access to.

     A collaborating sender/receiver pair can use a side channel to transfer
     information past the system's security mechanism, which is called a
     \emph{covert channel}. The simplicity of SKs enables the explicit
     consideration of the problem of covert channels, which are classified as
     data or timing channels.

     In a data channel, information may for example be hidden in metadata, such
     as using individual memory bits in an unconventional manner. The information
     to be transmitted is encoded by means of these bits, the receiver knows the
     special coding and is able to extract the data.

     Time channels use temporal variance of operations to transmit information.
     The receiver measures this variance and can thereby extract data bits. If a
     particular operation can be carried out quickly, then this is e.g.
     interpreted as 1; otherwise a 0 is assumed.

     As a general rule, only the required resources with minimal rights are
     available to both the kernel as well as subjects. This has the effect that
     the exposure of data is greatly reduced, minimizing the information which
     could be transferred via side channels. See also section
     \ref{datamodel_multicore} for further information on how data is handled in
     the Muen kernel.

     Data channels can be largely avoided or eliminated by careful assignment of
     resources to subjects in the system policy. On the other hand, timing
     channels require careful consideration of all shared resources and, in many
     cases, can only be limited in capacity by means of a suitable system
     structure.

     Muen offers the possibility to provide subjects with a coarse-grained time
     source, i.e. removing direct access to the hardware Time-Stamp Counter
     (TSC). Due to the low temporal resolution, observing a side channel is made
     significantly more difficult and thus the achievable transmission rate in
     practice is greatly reduced. In addition, subjects are preferably only
     assigned a single CPU, which prevents them from easily constructing a high
     resolution time source. The timed event mechanism also offers limited
     accuracy, since such events are only evaluated at the beginning of a minor
     frame.

     Deterministic scheduling can be leveraged to ensure that the amount of
     shared hardware (e.g. L1 cache, Branch Predictor Cache, Translation
     Lookaside-Buffer, etc.) between specific subjects is reduced. By
     appropriate configuration, it can be guaranteed that two subjects are not
     running on the same physical CPU or not concurrently on separate CPUs. If subjects
     are executed at different times, the observability of side channels and
     their bandwidth is limited since the sender and receiver must always
     alternate encoding and decoding of data. This also applies to subjects
     running on the same physical core, even though they still share a lot of
     hardware state. To further reduce bandwidth in this case, the integrator
     may explicitly schedule a subject, which "scrubs" the (micro-)architectural
     state, between the execution of other subjects.  Thus, the exact control
     over scheduling of subject enables system integrators to reduce the risk of
     side channels.

     Furthermore, on Muen systems, Hyper-Threading is always disabled because
     hardware threads share much more (micro-)architectural state than physical
     CPU cores.
    </text>
   </section>
  </section>

 <section id="datamodel" label="Data Model" priority="0">
  <section id="datamodel_multicore" label="Multicore Support" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Modern computers have an increasing number of CPU cores per processor. To
    utilize the hardware to its full potential, the Muen SK provides Multicore
    support.

    In a multicore system, a physical CPU provides more than one processor core
    in a single package. Additionally, systems equipped with Intel's
    Hyper-Threading Technology (HTT) have two or more \emph{logical CPUs} per
    core. A logical CPU is an execution unit of the processor that runs an
    application or a kernel process.

    Since HyperThreads located on the same CPU core share big parts of the
    micro-architectural state without effective means of isolation, Muen does
    not use HTT. It effectively disables HTT by only executing one hardware
    thread per physical CPU core.

    In MP systems, one processor termed \emph{bootstrap processor} (BSP) is
    responsible for system initialization, while the other processors, called
    \emph{application processors} (APs), wait for an initialization sequence as
    specified by Intel \cite{intelsdm}.

    At the basis of the multicore design is the symmetric execution of the
    kernel on each CPU core. This means that all cores execute an instance of
    exactly the same Muen kernel code. The only difference being, that parts of
    the system bring up code are exclusively run by the BSP.

    An important aspect of Muen's multicore design is that subjects are pinned
    to a specific CPU core. Subjects do not migrate between cores and are
    exclusively executed on the core defined by the associated subject
    specification in the system policy. This removes complexity from the kernel
    and the overall system by thwarting potential isolation issues which could
    be caused by the transfer of subjects and their state between cores. This
    design decision further simplifies the kernel implementation since no
    complex cross-core synchronization and migration algorithm has to be devised
    and implemented. Furthermore, each core can be restricted to only have
    access to the data structures associated with subjects it is tasked to
    execute.

    Since each CPU executes a distinct instance of the Muen kernel, by default,
    all kernel data is CPU-local, meaning it is not shared between kernels
    running on different CPUs. Global data is shared explicitly and is
    designated as such by placing it in a dedicated \texttt{.globaldata} linker
    section.
    One special case of a global data structure is the crash audit storage:
    while it is shared by all CPUs it may also be made accessible to subjects,
    e.g. for processing of crash information. Thus it is treated separately and
    not placed into the \texttt{.globaldata} linker section.

    Kernel data can be categorized as follows:
    \begin{enumerate}
     \item CPU-local data
     \item CPU-local, subject-related data
     \item Global data, shared by all CPUs
    \end{enumerate}

    Aside from these data structures, there are also interfaces used by the
    kernel to interact with external entities, such as memory-mapped devices
    like the IOMMU. The Tau0 interface is in the same category, as it is used by
    Tau0 to communicate with the kernel.

    The following sections provide explanations for each of the main kernel data
    categories.
   </text>
  </section>

  <section id="datamodel_cpulocal" label="CPU-local Data" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Library level data structures without special aspects (e.g. address clauses)
    are private, meaning each CPU has their own, local copy. This is achieved by
    providing each CPU with separate copies of the necessary binary sections
    (\texttt{.data} and \texttt{.bss}). Only the memory regions of sections
    belonging to a given CPU are mapped into the address space of that
    particular kernel.
   </text>
   <section id="datamodel_cpulocal_init" label="Initialization" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     Initialization of CPU-local data is performed by each CPU during
     Elaboration~\footnote{For a definition of elaboration, see Ada Reference
      Manual, 3.11.} via a call to adainit in the assembly startup code.
    </text>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="datamodel_local_subject" label="Local Subject-related Data" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Data structures associated with subjects, such as subject state or timed
    events, are implemented as arrays where each element is associated with a
    particular subject. The global subject ID is used as an index into the array
    to link an element to a specific subject. The array elements are dimensioned
    to 4K so they can be mapped as independent memory pages.

    These arrays are placed at specific virtual memory addresses. Only the
    elements belonging to subjects executed by a given CPU are mapped into the
    address space of that particular kernel. The correctness of the correspondence
    of subject and array element/index is checked by the validator tool.
    </text>
   <section id="datamodel_local_subject_init" label="Initialization" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     Each element is initialized by the executing CPU when the
     \texttt{SK.Scheduler.Init\_Subject} procedure is executed during system
     initialization.
    </text>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="datamodel_global" label="Global Shared Data" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Some data is accessed by all CPUs. This data is located in a separate,
    distinct linker section (\texttt{.globaldata}) which is backed by a single
    physical memory region, shared across all CPUs. Each kernel has a mapping of
    this region at the same memory location.

    Variable instances that are shared globally are placed in the linker section
    \texttt{.globaldata} via use of the Ada \texttt{Linker\_Section} aspect. By
    convention, concerned variables are prefixed with \texttt{Global\_}.
   </text>
   <section id="datamodel_global_init" label="Initialization" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     Initialization of global shared data is performed either via static
     initialization (if possible) or using explicit initialization procedures
     that are only executed by a single CPU, i.e. the BSP.
    </text>
   </section>
  </section>
 </section>

 <section id="interface_section" label="Kernel State" priority="0">
  <text priority="0">
   This section lists kernel data structures that are placed at specific memory
   addresses and used to maintain runtime state such as per-subject state
   descriptors. Furthermore external interfaces, e.g. for interaction with
   devices such as IOMMUs and I/O APIC are specified.
   The description includes the purpose as well as the memory representation of
   these interfaces.
  </text>
  <section id="interface_cpu_local" label="Per-CPU data" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Objects of category 1 in the kernel data model have a per-CPU copy and are
    distinct to each kernel running on a different CPU. Instances of these data
    structures are listed in this section.
   </text>
   <section id="SK.Scheduler.Current_Minor_Frame_ID" label="SK.Scheduler.Current_Minor_Frame_ID" priority="0"/>
   <section id="SK.Scheduler.Scheduling_Groups" label="SK.Scheduler.SK.Scheduler.Scheduling_Groups" priority="0"/>
   <section id="SK.Interrupt_Tables.Instance" label="SK.Interrupt_Tables.Instance" priority="0"/>
  </section>
  <section id="Skp.IOMMU.IOMMUs" label="Skp.IOMMU.IOMMUs" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    External interface used to access and program IOMMU(s), see also section
    \ref{kernel_devs_iommu}.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="SK.IO_Apic.Register_Select" label="SK.IO_Apic.Register_Select" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    External interface used in conjunction with \ref{SK.IO_Apic.Window} to
    access and program the I/O APIC, see also section \ref{kernel_devs_apic}.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="SK.IO_Apic.Window" label="SK.IO_Apic.Window" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    External interface used in conjunction with \ref{SK.IO_Apic.Register_Select}
    to access and program the I/O APIC, see also section \ref{kernel_devs_apic}.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="SK.Crash_Audit.Instance" label="SK.Crash_Audit.Instance" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Global crash audit information data structure. It is \emph{not} put in the
    CPU-Global section since it may be accessible by subjects (e.g. for
    outputting crash information). Additionally the memory type of the region
    must be Uncached (UC) so the content survives a warm start/system reboot.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="SK.Tau0_Interface.New_Major" label="SK.Tau0_Interface.New_Major" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    External interface to \tau0.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="SK.FPU.Subject_FPU_States" label="SK.FPU.Subject_FPU_States" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Local subject-related data, see section \ref{datamodel_local_subject}.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="SK.Scheduling_Info.Sched_Info" label="SK.Scheduling_Info.Sched_Info" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Local subject-related data, see section \ref{datamodel_local_subject}.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="SK.Subjects.Descriptors" label="SK.Subjects.Descriptors" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Local subject-related data, see section \ref{datamodel_local_subject}.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="SK.Subjects_Interrupts.Pending_Interrupts" label="SK.Subjects_Interrupts.Pending_Interrupts" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Local subject-related data, see section \ref{datamodel_local_subject}.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="SK.Subjects_MSR_Store.MSR_Storage" label="SK.Subjects_MSR_Store.MSR_Storage" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Local subject-related data, see section \ref{datamodel_local_subject}.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="SK.Timed_Events.Subject_Events" label="SK.Timed_Events.Subject_Events" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Local subject-related data, see section \ref{datamodel_local_subject}.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="SK.VMX.VMCS" label="SK.VMX.VMCS" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Local subject-related data, see section \ref{datamodel_local_subject}.
   </text>
  </section>
 </section>

 <section id="cpu_global_variables_section" label="CPU-Global State" priority="0">
  <text priority="0">
   This section lists global data structures that are shared across CPU cores
   via the \texttt{globaldata} linker section, describing their purpose. All the
   instances presented below fall into the data model category 3 described in
   section \ref{datamodel_global}.

   Aspects are Ada/SPARK language level constructs that determine operational
   properties of variable instances. The following aspects are referenced in
   this chapter:

   \begin{description}
    \item[Async\_Readers] \hfill \\
     A component external to the program might read a value written to the
     object at any time, see SPARK 2014 Reference Manual, section 7.1.2
     \cite{SPARK2014}.
    \item[Async\_Writers] \hfill \\
     A component external to the program might update the value of an object at
     any time, see SPARK 2014 Reference Manual, section 7.1.2 \cite{SPARK2014}.
    \item[Volatile] \hfill \\
     The compiler is instructed to include each read and update of a volatile
     object, see Ada Language Reference Manual, C.6/20 \cite{Ada2012}.
   \end{description}
  </text>
 </section>

 <section id="kernel_devices" label="Devices" priority="0">
  <text priority="0">
   This section describes what I/O devices the kernel uses and for what purpose.
  </text>
  <section id="kernel_devs_apic" label="Interrupt Controllers" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    The kernel controls and programs all interrupt controllers since it must
    ensure that only IRQs according to the policy are generated and routed to the
    assigned subject, and thus CPU. On x86, there are three different interrupt
    controllers that must be considered: PIC, APIC and I/O APIC.

    The legacy PIC is disabled since only the APIC and I/O APIC are used. The
    APIC is CPU-local and is setup during system initialization by each CPU
    core. The I/O APIC and its interrupt routing table is programmed by the BSP
    according to the system policy.

    During normal operation, the APIC is accessed to acknowledge
    End-Of-Interrupt (EOI) whenever an IRQ is handled, in order to unblock
    processing of other interrupts. In case of level-triggered IRQs, the I/O
    APIC is used to mask and unmask the corresponding redirection table entries.

    Enforcement that only the configured interrupts are raised is done by the
    IOMMU Interrupt Remapping functionality, see section
    \ref{kernel_devs_iommu}.

    \begin{info}
    Note that IRQs raised via the I/O APIC are \emph{also} routed through the
    IOMMU and thus affected by interrupt remapping.
    \end{info}
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="kernel_devs_iommu" label="IOMMU" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    The IOMMU performs two critical functions to constrain devices to only
    access resources and raise interrupts as defined in the system policy: DMA
    Remapping and Interrupt Remapping.

    DMA Remapping (DMAR) performs address translation for device memory access,
    analogous how the MMU operates for subjects. Each DMA request is identified
    by the device source ID which is associated with the VT-d page tables
    generated for the given device. During startup, the kernel installs the
    pre-generated data structure and activates DMAR by programming
    the IOMMU. For further information see Intel VT-d Specification, "3 DMA
    Remapping" \cite{intelvtd}.

    The IOMMU Interrupt Remapping (IR) feature with the remapping table
    generated during integration assures that only the correct interrupt vectors are
    raised according to the policy for all assigned IRQs and that all other,
    non-assigned IRQs are blocked. During setup, the kernel installs the
    remapping table and enables IR. For further information see Intel VT-d
    Specification, "5 Interrupt Remapping" \cite{intelvtd}.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="kernel_devs_timer" label="Timer" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    Muen uses the VMX-preemption timer as the timing source to realize
    preemption of subjects when a minor frame expires. It is a per-CPU timer,
    which is programmed by writing a countdown value in the corresponding VMCS
    field. In VMX non-root mode, the VMX-preemption timer counts down at a rate
    proportional to the TSC and causes a VM-exit when the counter reaches zero.
    For further documentation see Intel SDM Vol. 3C, "25.5.1 VMX-Preemption
    Timer".

    Note that Muen only supports systems that have the "Invariant TSC" feature,
    see Intel SDM Vol. 3B, "17.17.1 Invariant TSC".
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="kernel_devs_debug" label="Diagnostics" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    The debug build of the Muen SK provides additional debug information at
    runtime via an I/O device. This output can provide system integrators
    and developers with additional information, e.g. in an unexpected error case,
    the crash audit information is output via the I/O device on top of
    writing it to the crash audit memory region. Which hardware device the kernel
    uses for diagnostics, if any, is specified in the system policy.

    All debug output statements in the kernel are enclosed in \texttt{pragma
    Debug}. This has the effect that none of them are present in the release
    version of the kernel as they are automatically removed by the compiler.
   </text>
  </section>
 </section>

 <section id="verification_and_validation" label="Verification" priority="20">
  <text priority="0">
   This section describes the formal methods and techniques applied to the
   verification of Muen.
  </text>
  <section id="verification_spark" label="SPARK" priority="-10">
   <text priority="0">
    SPARK is the primary technology used for the formal verification of Muen and
    particularly trustworthy components such as $\tau$0. It enables data and
    information flow analysis as well as the proof of absence of runtime errors.
    The necessary proofs are produced by the SPARK GNATprove tools which in turn
    use automated theorem provers, like the Z3 SMT
    solver\footnote{\url{https://github.com/Z3Prover/z3}} for example.
    Application of the GNATprove tools guarantees that the SPARK language rules
    are adhered to at all time and that the analyzed source code is valid.

    The proof of advanced functional features is realized with the help of the
    interactive theorem prover
    Isabelle\footnote{\url{https://isabelle.in.tum.de}}. Abstract properties
    are formalized in Isabelle/HOL. These possibly complex, external
    specifications are linked to the SPARK implementation by so-called
    \emph{Ghost Code}. The GNATprove tool generates verification conditions in
    the Why3 language, which are imported into Isabelle by means of a driver.
    This way, the correspondence of the SPARK source code to an abstract, formal
    specification can be shown.

    The interaction of the tools used for the verification is shown
    schematically in figure \ref{fig:spark-toolchain}.

    \begin{figure}[ht]
     \centering
     \input{graph_spark}
     \caption{Toolchain for the verification of SPARK programs.}
     \label{fig:spark-toolchain}
    \end{figure}
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="verification_conditions_spark2014" label="SPARK 2014">
   <text priority="0">
    This section shows the summary of the verification results for all checks
    performed by SPARK/GNATprove in the Muen kernel project. For a detailed
    description of each line of the summary table please refer to the SPARK 2014
    user guide~\footnote{\url{https://docs.adacore.com/spark2014-docs/html/ug/en/source/how_to_view_gnatprove_output.html\#the-analysis-results-summary-file}}.
   </text>
  </section>
 </section>

 <section id="implementation" label="Implementation" priority="0">
  <text priority="0">
   This chapter describes the implementation of the Muen Kernel. To
   avoid/minimize divergence between this documentation and the actual
   implementation, the content of these sections is extracted from source code
   annotations.
  </text>
  <section id="implementation_entry_points" label="Kernel Entry Points" priority="-20">
   <text priority="0">
    As already mentioned in section \ref{overview_operation} the kernel
    control-flow is kept very simple and only has two entry points with the
    following (symbol) names:
    \begin{itemize}
     \item Startup: \verb!kernel_entry_point! (Assembler) \rightarrow \verb!sk_initialize! (SPARK)
     \item Scheduler Loop: \verb!vmx_exit_handler! (Assembler) \rightarrow \verb!handle_vmx_exit! (SPARK)
    \end{itemize}

    The assembler symbol is where the respective code flow starts which after
    some low-level steps then calls the mentioned SPARK subprogram.
   </text>
   <section id="implementation_entry_points_startup" label="System Startup" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     After loading the Muen system image, a bootloader starts execution of the
     Muen code at the entry point \verb!kernel_entry_point! in file
     \verb!kernel/src/asm/init.S!. After low-level system/CPU initialization,
     the procedure \verb!SK.Kernel.Initialize! in
     \verb!kernel/src/sk-kernel.ads! is called via the exported symbol
     \verb!sk_initialize!. Section \ref{impl_kernel_init} describes the kernel
     initialization process performed by this procedure.
    </text>
   </section>
   <section id="implementation_entry_points_scheduler" label="Scheduler Loop" priority="0">
    <text priority="0">
     Whenever a VM-Exit occurs, the CPU passes the thread of execution from the subject
     code running in VMX non-root mode to the kernel \verb!handle_vmx_exit! procedure
     found in file \verb!kernel/src/sk-scheduler.ads!. The hardware stores the
     execution state of the subject in the VMCS, transitions to VMX root-mode by
     restoring the host state of the kernel and starts execution at the Exit
     handler. Section \ref{impl_exit_handler} describes the main scheduler loop
     of the Muen kernel.
    </text>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section id="impl_subjects_state" label="Subject State Management" priority="-2">
   <text priority="0">
    This section describes how the state of subjects is managed by the kernel.
    While the subject is running, it may execute allowed CPU instructions until
    a VM exit into the kernel occurs. At this point, the CPU stores the current
    execution state in the associated VMCS. To enable subject monitors to change
    the state of monitored subjects, the kernel saves values from the VMCS to
    the associate subject state data structure in memory (see section
    \ref{SK.Subjects.Descriptors}). Prior to executing a subject, the subject
    state has to be restored back into the associated VMCS.
   </text>
  </section>
  <section id="impl_vmcs" label="VMCS Management" priority="0">
   <text priority="0">
    This section describes how the VMCS structures associated with subjects are
    managed by the kernel. A VMCS controls the execution environment of a
    subject, e.g. what hardware features/privileged instructions a subject may
    execute etc. While transitioning between VMX root and non-root mode, the
    hardware automatically saves and restores the state to/from the current
    VMCS depending on how it has been configured. Part of the kernel's duties is
    to set up the VMCS according to the subject specification in the system
    policy.
   </text>
  </section>
 </section>

</doc>
